howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is nadav zimmer a
principal
in harlem in public high school in new
york city
he's also the author of a very
interesting book
education in the digital age how we get
there
thanks nadav great to have you here it's
such a pleasure to be here jim
i heard about your book and i think it
was from probably your publicist
actually and i checked it out and i said
hell yes this is a theme that we've
talked about here on the show before
we had uh zach stein on actually for
three episodes
he wrote the preface to the book yeah i
saw that good job that he did
extraordinarily interesting guy
this is a different take i would say in
many ways a more tangible take
on envisioning what a new education for
the modern age might look like
you know the book is really interesting
you must have done a tremendous amount
of research on it
because you recapitulate the history and
mechanics of debt and money
the rise and fall of economic paradigms
the history of technology
the obsolescence of econ 101
sense making and lots more of the kinds
of things that we talk about on the show
but mostly not exclusively mostly we're
going to focus today
on your ideas of building an entirely
new educational infrastructure in fact
probably
better to say an educational ecosystem
now of course we'll refer back to some
of that earlier material in the book and
i do recommend it to listeners as a good
and clear and
commonsensical and that's key
presentation of many of the ideas we
talk about on the show
absolutely thank you and as usual we
will have links to the book
and anything else that's mentioned here
on the episode page on the show
just go to jimrutshow.com and check out
the episode page for this episode
let's start with a brief story of your
career you graduated from college
and then what happened so graduated from
college with a degree in
physics but i did a lot of computer
science and
to help pay for my college i always
worked and so i worked in the
information technology the
student services where people go to the
computer lab and help desk for
professors and such
and i spent one summer during college
working at a bank
doing some software uh work and so
after college i went out to silicon
valley with my girlfriend who was from
around there
and got a job at ford digital equipment
corp in palo alto but i worked
my day-to-day job was actually at
netscape i went into software
engineering and then did some consulting
work and
ran a metal fabrication studio at some
point
and then came to new york to care for my
grandparents and i was still doing the
consulting thing so i could do that and
working for
new york offices doing the same kind of
i.t infrastructure consulting
and then suddenly became a high school
physics teacher robotics teacher and
then high school principal
i needed to go the private sector route
to prove some things to myself i think
and when i got that big job offer that i
was waiting for
i suddenly didn't say no i didn't say
yes and that surprised me it took me a
few weeks to
figure out that i just needed that offer
i actually didn't want that job
i like to work really hard and i like
complicated things
and so doing that to make money i felt
like i'd get resentful at some point but
doing that for high school kids
i just couldn't imagine ever resenting
working hard for that so it made sense
to go there
earlier in my career before i went too
deep and so then i ended up here
really amazing uh amazing story really a
gutsy move i mean how many people at a
relatively young age
turn down the career track right the big
bucks glory maybe
maybe not for a truly fulfilling and
moderately uh big city teachers are paid
pretty good these days
a moderate lifestyle but certainly no
glory shall we say at least to the
external world i really commend you for
that decision it was a selfish decision
right it was for myself but yeah here i
hear what you're saying from the outside
it might look
altruistic but it really is for my own
quality of life of course in some sense
nobody's actually an altruist right
i think we actually all know that you
just have to understand what people's
motivations
actually are right seldom do people
actually work against their own
interests
and then you worked your way up from
school teacher to principal and
into a pretty uh tough school in harlem
it had low rankings
and over a period of years you moved the
rankings from the bottom to the top how
did you do that
so my staff did that i really believe as
a principal as a school leader in a
school the teachers who have contact
with the young people are the leaders
and so first step was leadership support
and learning from my staff
and learning from the right staff my art
teacher was kind of my main go-to person
for all professional development because
kind of that entry
i understood that the complexity that
comes with interpreting a piece of art
was the kind of thinking that i wanted
the kids to be doing so it was a focus
on looking at what
is critical thinking and i had for a
long time actually since the late 90s
been looking at decentralized media i
had started a podcasting non-profit
before podcasting was known as such we
still distributed on cd magazines
because the internet couldn't handle
audio yet
and so i kind of was lucky to come into
education with the
software engineering background and with
the media savvy and so
that idea of having high quality student
work products
in the form of media you know podcasts
or videos and focusing on just
generating really high quality content
generated by the students
that led to seven year journey but what
was surprising for us nobody expected
our data to be that strong because the
data
is based on standardized tests mostly
and i wasn't focusing on those my risk
the risk that i took and i knew i could
get a job back in technology so i knew i
could take the
take the risk and get fired but i took a
risk of kind of not focusing on the
standardized exams and
within 18 months we were we went from an
f school
on a shutdown list persistent low
achieving school need of improving all
these
acronyms they step on you and all these
state intervention teams and auditors
all over crawling around the building
because we're about to get shut down
within 18 months we were a b-school in a
school and maintained that a
top ranking for you know seven years so
that surprised me i had seen a little
bit of that
with my robotics team when i brought in
media and we um we made a documentary
somebody made a documentary about the
team
there's some kind of executive function
of self-reflection that happens when
somebody's making a documentary about
you
that i just brought into individual
students lives um and the other thing
i'd say about that is i'm really
data-driven
but i you know data is like a menu right
you don't need the menu
so the data would just let me know which
students to go talk to when
and about what but it wasn't the um
that played a big role in our success i
think but it uh you know so for example
i would
look to see changes in student
performance and so if a student's
attendance went down or the
the assignment they get at the beginning
of class they do now if suddenly they
were always doing well on those suddenly
that dropped off
i knew something had changed and i would
just ask them what change you know just
pull them into office privately
one-on-one and say hey what what
happened or have a counselor do that
and conversely you could have a student
that's failing all their classes you
know
and one week they're passing all of them
if you just look at aggregate statistics
of that
the school they're still failing all
their classes but if you can get that
change for that week you can go grab
them in the halls and say what the hell
happened you passed all your classes
this week
there's no official grades there's no
report cards but that
high it's kind of a high frequency
heartbeat
more than most schools that just give
you data at the very end of the term
after you know months of learning we
looked at gating data earlier
so that we could intervene on both sides
of acknowledging students and supporting
them
that sounds like the way it ought to be
and unfortunately oftentimes isn't
what's the name of the documentary by
the way maybe talk just a little bit
about that robotics team does that seem
to me a pretty interesting story
yeah i can send you a link to it it's on
youtube now it was called the g house
pirates
which was the name of the team cool and
basically they went from a
school that nobody would expect to do
well in such a competition to one of the
top teams right
we were the first all-minority team to
compete nationally we beat all the
private schools and public schools but
right all the private schools included
we beat in
new york city second place in new york
state um and that includes you know
rochester
like these massive teams that have
massive industry behind them um
and we were able to take them down just
with brute force i mean for the six
we had six weeks to build the robot this
you know five foot tall
120 pound monster and we i lived at the
school
during those six weeks i you know i'm
not not supposed to tell anyone that
because
we're not supposed to stay overnight at
the school but we i had a cot in the lab
and
we would work through the night for six
weeks i did not and i didn't have a
family back then so i could do those
crazy things but
that's how we pulled it off is just
brute force you and i both know
oftentimes
it's perspiration not inspiration that's
the answer it was that thomas edison i
think said that
i don't remember how many times it
appeared in your book but the word work
ethic is a word you use a lot
yeah and people you know across the
political spectrum agree that
it's kind of uh we're losing it you know
um because screens are sucking our
attention and we don't realize that
we're
handing over value to the screen instead
of using the screen
to support us to you know meet the goals
that we're setting for ourselves which
is a true digital native i think would
be using the screen to generate
value rather than letting it suck value
from their life
but there's an issue with critical
thinking i think and with
work what you call work ethic just being
able to say declare you're going to do
something and get it done
that is a weak muscle among our people
in our society generally in our youth in
particular
yeah i hear it from a lot of employers
that you know people that have jobs that
require
you know serious attention to detail you
know really
hardcore stuff like talking to a guy who
has a roofing business
they do high-end custom roofs and
repairs on custom
roofs you really have to know what
you're doing you're operating on a roof
right you can easily fall off and break
your ass and
he's got eight open jobs that pay damn
well
doesn't require any higher education and
he's basically just looking for high
work ethic non-drug using
attention to detail kind of people and
he says he can't find them
here in the middle of a pandemic with a
15 unemployment rate
yep that's amazing but not that shocking
and i think that what you mentioned
about drug
use you know legal or illegal i think
everybody's drugged up because we don't
have that work ethic actually working
hard and the rewards the psychoactive
rewards you get from accomplishing
things um is what those drugs are
filling in for i think i think there's a
human need to do hard work and to
feel successful in your own right with
your own standards
and without that i think we all you know
everybody's medicating themselves in one
way or another
yeah and then attention to detail also
you know the essence of our current
economy as you go into in the book is
essentially
attention hijacking we'll get to that a
little bit later
so we have a school system and you know
through
dedicated and perhaps wild and crazy
principles sometimes you can make it
work for the kids
but everything we read says that
particularly for the more deprived kids
it ain't working so well and i would
tell you looking at the kids even in
middle class and upper middle class
schools maybe it works sort of sometimes
but at extremely high cost
to their well-being i mean i look back
at the college entrance
craziness that goes on these days you
know i was in college i filled out a
couple apps threw them over the transom
and you saw what happened didn't sweat
it right
and that was that like i applied to two
colleges got into both of them picked
one that was that but
now oh my god and so there's some sense
a significant
mismatch between our educational called
the
public school system and those private
schools that more or less emulate the
public schools
not all of them but many of them we do
have some alternatives like the waldorf
schools etc
but talk a little bit about the mismatch
between the
educational industrial complex and what
our economy really needs
right so 1843 horace mann brings johann
gottlieb
fiesta's ideas right into the us and
it's this industrial
idea of you know kind of taking the
ideas from industrial production and
bringing them into human thought
1892 they pulled together a committee of
10 they designed the high school as we
know it today
and what you're pointing out is that
we're in an educational system that
it has existed since then at least right
this industrial model
and since then the digital age has taken
hold and decentralization is happening
and so the mismatch is one um you know
critical thinking
or thinking about your purpose or
thinking creatively or solving difficult
problems is not what you needed factory
workers to be doing with their time
and the the industrial model of
education was brilliant
for what it was designed to do and it's
outlived its usefulness because it was
so effective it's hard to let go of
because it was such an effective tool
to increase literacy and numeracy and
it had a lot of other impacts i think
that were really positive but today it's
just
outlived its usefulness and we're living
in a world that's still run by those
schools
so that's kind of the big context now
getting into some of the details
the system right now is top down it's
based it's coercive
right it forces you to sit in and i'm
thinking about high school that's my
area of expertise i think it's very
different you mentioned waldorf schools
i grew up in the waldorf schools in
elementary but i think that's a
different beast
for high school where you sit in a room
for you know 42 minutes and then the
bell rings and you go to another subject
that's all the industrial bells and
carnegie units where seat time is how
you measure learning
it's a system that was designed for
industrial production and it's just
not useful anymore and our kids know it
no matter how much money we pump into
education we don't get better results
even on these standardized exams that
the same people get to control they
can't even fudge the numbers
because the kids know that the system is
no longer relevant
i'll let you lead us into different
avenues of that but it's the same
mismatch
that industrial companies are facing
when there's inversion right when the
cab company gets faced with uber when
the
hotel market for travelers gets
challenged by airbnb
those are the same pressures that our
schools are feeling but as a
public school system they don't fall
apart in the same way because they're
too big to fail in a sense
and so the transition is going to be one
where we're
you know rebuilding it while we're in
flight and so it's a little bit
different of a process but
it's the same pressures of inversion
that are happening in industry
as are happening in our high schools
yeah truthfully this
sense of mismatch has been going on for
quite a while i'm a bit of an old stir i
went to high school in the late
60s and even then we had the sense that
well yeah you hop through the hoops and
you know get the reward go to a good
college if you did go to college i
actually went to a
working class high school where only 20
of the people went on to a four-year
college
even then we felt that there was
something wrong with the sausage factory
as we sometimes call it that it was not
a
humane use for human beings and as i was
reading in your book
you know i really came away resonating
saying hmm this would have been a hell
of a lot more fun
in addition to being a better
preparation for the world of 1971 let
alone the world of 2021.
maybe talk a little bit about that soul
suck
that the sausage factory has as one of
its side products
right so the main engine that drove the
economy and our high schools were
designed to prepare kids for this engine
is
make stuff so we can create jobs so we
can
have people buy more stuff so that we
can have more jobs right that was the
loop that ran everything
um and so we were trained in high school
to be consumers
and that includes consumers of how to
think right from the textbooks and the
standardization of thinking in the
standardized tests
today to make money you have to be a
producer of content right you have to
get an audience
you have to have people follow you and
then that
audience is what starts generating money
in a digital economy that attention
people's attention
so there's it's just a very different
way to think because the old industrial
model was based on things like fossil
fuels where it was zero sum i have it or
you have it we can't both have it
but information in an information age or
an ideas economy you want things to
get copied and spread the more somebody
spreads your tweet the more
social capital you gain so it's a
collaborative positive sum dynamic
and that change from a top-down coercive
system to a bottom-up collaborative
system
it can't be gradual the classroom when
you walk into classroom when i walk into
classroom as a principal
i can see the ones that are bottom up
where the students are generating the
learning
where it's their genius that's at you
know on display and then you can see the
ones where it's the teachers genius on
display and the students are there
told to mimic and regurgitate it's a
flip right it's a switch it's not a
it's not a fader and so that's that's
where we see ourselves right now i think
at with covet in particular
we're hitting a breaking point where um
we're either gonna have to flip the
switch or our schools are gonna
just completely fall apart no one's
going to go to them
yep it's an opportunity right it's an
opportunity to accelerate
a change that was likely to happen
someday i think the same applies for
instance to business travel
for at least 10 years i've been telling
people why you need to fly around the
country for a one hour meeting spend two
thousand dollars in three days
when zoom or earlier skype would work
almost as good
maybe better instead of spending an hour
spend two hours on the meeting
and i believe covid has thrown a shock
to that basin of attraction
of high-end business travel high and
medium and business travel
and i suspect it'll never go back it may
well be that the same will happen
with education that's right it may or
may not i hope it does and i think
you're right that this is an opportunity
because people's minds are open
i've been doing this work with media in
high schools since 2003 so you know 17
years
and all of a sudden people are willing
to see what i've been seeing what what
people that my teachers have been
seeing that that shift from students
asking will this be on the test
right and wondering what the brand of
thinking they need to
regurgitate is for that test flipping
over to
students producing quality work and
focusing on that student content
as the measure rather than the
standardized test as the measure because
that
just measures how good of a robot you've
become and we're not we have robots now
we don't need people to act like robots
anymore
yeah all right now the one thing that i
raised my eyebrow at a few times in the
book
let me explain what you really had in
mind here
was very strong focus on
digital native artifacts podcasts videos
etc
as an end in themselves and as entering
into what you call the dopamine opioid
economy
is that really what we want for our
civilization to have
ever higher level of attention hijacking
ever
higher levels of simulation nobody out
getting their toes in the soil nobody
making anything
you know i gotta say i'm a little
skeptical of
at least where at a first order naive
read that approach would seem to head
so there are two pieces there i totally
agree with you that the screenification
the
hijacking of our attention that is not
digital native digital natives are the
ones that are going to
learn to resist those uh forces
and generate value on themselves the
economies the cultures that learn how to
produce content
are gonna be the ones that make money
not the ones that are consuming it not
the ones that are you know
beholden to the apps and pouring their
attention into it for others to control
and others to manipulate my proposal
here the innovation in what i call
academic capital
is based on uploading a representation
of your work as a podcast as a video as
code but it's not that people aren't
getting their toes
in the water i think high school should
not be students sitting in classrooms it
should be students out in a protest
covering it as journalists and telling
that story preparing before they go with
what questions they're going to ask in
the historical context
coming back and editing i want them out
interviewing
the elders in their community doing
projects interacting with the world to
understand physics
and you can do that now with your phone
and document it and shoot you know and
edit
and make something that's researched and
revised and relevant to what they're
interested in
what's important now is that we teach
students skills
that will give them the critical
thinking so that they cannot be
manipulated for
economic gain they can't have the
corporations manipulate them to buy
things and they can't have the
politicians manipulate them to fit into
a box
our democracy and our economy become
anti-fragile when people can think in
more complicated
complex ways and have their own
positions that are not the same as
everybody around them
so that diversity of thought and of
experience is what i'm after
so take airbnb airbnb is very much a
physical thing people are going on
vacation and actually staying in these
places
but they are required to enter the
digital realm by taking photos of their
place and entering a description and
putting in the rules
and saying whether they have a washer
dryer or not and by entering those forms
into database and having visual
representations
on the platform you can then create this
platform what you were talking about
before the ecosystem
so there is a piece that things have to
get digitized i mean i'm recommending
using podcasts in particular that's my
favorite format
um you can also do video i you know
prefer podcasts
or code and there are many other things
you can you know tell your story now
but the story should be one of you
getting out of the classroom especially
in 11th and 12th grade going into the
community
and really being like journalists and
for the social studies and
you know english credits in particular
for the humanities you should be out in
the real world
and we shouldn't have to tell you what
the content you're going to study is
we're going to tell you the skills
here's how to do research right here's
how to write a script here's how to do
fact checking here's how to prepare for
questions open-ended close-ended
we're going to give those skills and let
the students apply the academic skills
to the content that interests them
so the content they're producing is
nuanced and revised so i'm not talking
about academic capital is distinct from
social capital social capital you whip
out your camera you do something
spontaneous and you send it to the world
you do it a thousand times a day
academic capital you upload once a month
you spend the whole month on one
ten minute piece max 10 minutes right no
more than that
whole month editing revising multiple
revisions getting feedback
doing the research doing the writing
reshooting all of that to produce one
piece a month that is academically
rigorous that is nuanced that is
researched
and that represents the skills that the
educators put out for you to be
practicing like at a gym that you have
to
over and over exercise certain skill
until you got good enough at it
even if it's editing um that you produce
something that's professional quality so
that's what academic capital is and it
does depend you're right on youth media
being the representation of capital in
the place of standardized exams
but i want kids out there in the world
with their cameras i don't want them in
the classroom
and i don't want them in their phones i
guess one thing i would push one step
further is you know once a high school
kid develops the skills to
document and present work
might not it be also good to encourage
them to actually develop some
fundamental skills in the real world you
know have them do a video of themselves
taking apart and reassembling an ar-15
or something right or
rebuilding a lawnmower engine because
again i think that one of the
problems of our whole society is that so
many kids
today are retreating away from the
physical the actual the hands-on
and are living more in this purely
digital age and i don't say this as a
ludite and i do
recall you told the story of old ned
ludd
in the book i go back to the very
beginning of the online world i worked
at the very first consumer online
service a company called the source
in 1980 in fact i designed their second
generation email system
their second generation bulletin board
forum system
and i was a product manager and what was
probably the very first
social media platform something called
participate so i go way back so
by no means a luddite but to define
all of life in terms of creating digital
artifacts and not focusing
on the skills that are documented
strikes me as
only making one step not two no i
totally i totally totally agree with you
i grew up in
the uh vocational tech i was a physics
teacher and the robotics teacher at a
vocational
high school um and so that vocational
piece being in the shop and working
um with your hands is is what education
has to look like i
completely agree with you and so the
system that i'm designing allows
teachers vocational teachers robotics
teachers in particular i've obviously
thought a lot about
them as i designed this allows them to
create a credit
the system decentralizes the creation of
credit so anybody can make a credit
and they can make a credit that's based
on those real world experiences and i
think you're right that we have to get
students
out of their devices into the real world
to interact with it
it's not about getting them you know
their attention
into some app that's capturing their
attention we talked before a little bit
about the old industrial loop that was
you get more jobs by producing more
stuff so that people can
you know get more jobs because they have
to produce more stuff the new cycle that
i talk about in the book
is you create something you share it and
you get
data right and that cycle people um you
know
whether you're building chairs for a
living or highways
or podcasts it's still a similar cycle
of creation and sharing and
getting data back and so that is what i
want students to engage with
and i agree with you i want the credits
on the system to be ones that ask you to
go out into the world and to go into a
wood shop and to
work with your hands and take apart
machinery like be curious about the
world and interact with your world
socially physically for the different
disciplines that you're studying
i can't imagine how a physics credit
could ever
keep you in a screen there's no way to
study physics with a screen
right you need to get out and you know
bounce a ball throw you know make a
pendulum whatever it is
and similarly with chemistry but i think
that you can do a lot of that
and capture your work in instead of uh
you know scientist journal that they
used to do on paper you can do it as a
podcast just pick up and
speak a little bit and then edit it
together at the end it's the piece of
the audio or video
just adds a piece of reflection so if
you want to have an intern at any
business
you could use this system for to have
interns as high school students
and they just the podcasting just gives
a way to reflect over the whole
experience and at the end wrap up and do
a reflection and that reflective piece
is important to learning that
metacognitive piece is important to
learning
and so i think it always benefits from
having the
that's why i got that data in the school
to move so quickly because
students were being recorded and they
could then hear what they
said there's something in that process
of recording and listening and then
thinking about and recording again and
journaling it's like keeping a journal
that process can always support any work
that you do but i totally agree with you
that we cannot
if this has kids end up in the screens
more we have failed
indeed you also and enough to tie back
this to actual world projects
you have actually quite eloquent one of
the better discussions i've ever read
about crowd funding and how it's a pull
model rather than a push
model for creation right you know the
traditional
this more or less ripping off your
rhetoric here so this isn't my idea this
is yours
you know the traditional big industrial
corporation you know designs a
new widget that makes life a little
easier sells it for a while and then
sales start going down so they come out
with the new and improved version
and push it out into the world if you're
proctor and gamble you spend
two billion dollars a year on
advertising for new and improved tide
and many other products which haven't
changed really in any fundamental way in
50 years
while crowdfunding is very much the
opposite right you have an idea
you put it out there and if people
resonate with it and pre-commit
then you build it right quite
interesting and it would seem to me that
in this model of encouraging the
high school age kid to engage with the
world crowd funding could be a
remarkable way
first they have to learn the technique
right you don't want to have them use it
on real bullets on the very first one
but maybe the second one they may
actually
put up a crowd funding proposal that
they're prepared to execute upon
should it actually gather some attention
absolutely and so that
model of the crowd intelligence
driving the work rather than a ceo at
the top deciding
you know what's going to happen um map
that onto a classroom
right it fits perfectly the old the ceo
was the model of the teacher
that would tell the students they would
be the manager of the classroom and they
would do a lot of classroom management
right
and it was all about controlling
coercing and warehousing our young
people
and increasingly the more they
understand that what they're learning is
irrelevant the more we have to
focus on coercion to keep them in those
damn classrooms
studying this crap that comes from a
textbook that's totally out of date
imagine if the students are creating the
content that's what i'm talking about
here with these credits
if the students are the ones creating
the content that that is the
crowdsourced
model working in the classroom and a
project a great project is to actually
do a
crowdsource model in the business sense
where you put out an idea and try to get
it pre-funded
whether they succeed or fail they'll
learn a ton from that but
the model itself of crowdsourcing the
information and all i'm saying with the
digital media
going back to what we're talking about
before the role of recording your
process
with audio or with video i think audio
is more intimate again and easier
but if you record the process with audio
that becomes the accountability for the
teacher so you can be out in the field
doing the work and the accountability
for the teacher instead of asking you to
take an exam at the end the teacher
knows did you do anything they need to
know did you do anything what did you do
and so editing the audio and sharing
your process back with the teacher
in a podcast format would be how the
teacher evaluates
your work because they weren't there
with you they don't have to be there
with you when you're in 11th and 12th
grade you should be out
learning on your own and so the i
totally agree that mapping that is the
key innovation here is mapping that
crowdsourcing model
into classrooms in high school
interesting
one last question before we get down
into the nitty-gritty of your dna
system proposal as i said i've been
involved with the online world since
literally the beginning been involved
with many companies
either as an employee or an advisor an
investor and one thing has held
remarkably true
over the last 40 years which is in
online platforms approximately two
percent of the people
provide fifty percent of the content
two percent provide fifty percent and so
i'd
say is it a reasonable expectation that
you can get
a large percentage of the kids to become
creators
on essentially a similar level of
productivity you mentioned
what was it once a month right maybe
maybe
it's only a small percentage that have
the right set
of emotional mental drive
characteristics that allow them to be
high quality
relatively high volume producers is it
reasonable that we can all become such
yeah i think in high school it is in
universities when you when you want a
degree
you're willing to you know if we were
just asking them to spontaneously do
this on the united say hey you know hey
kids
let's have you do some academic skill
test building
i don't think any kid will do that um
but they have to because they're in
school
so we kind of have them captive and
right now what we're asking them to do
is learn how to master taking
standardized tests and what a shame what
it
what a misuse of their human potential
to have them studying that instead of
having them study how to make a podcast
it's not
that difficult to learn how to edit
audio enough
and or build a team where you have you
know you do the minimum so you know what
you need to know but you don't need to
get more than one editing credit
if you work with a team of young people
here's here's a sample of what worked at
my school
we usually would have three roles one
person would be in front of the camera
delivering the content to the camera
right somebody else would have been the
one to write that content to write the
script
and to research it and somebody else
would be doing the audio and video
you know and that piece doing the
technical side and so a team of three
then can work together
and if you are someone who's not as
strong on the reading and writing and
research
you get to start by being the one on
camera looking smart and sounding smart
with somebody else's ideas and that
tends to appeal to to those kids i had
kids that were illiterate couldn't copy
a sentence you wrote down a sentence or
printed a sentence and they couldn't
copy and add another sheet of paper
right
but you give them a microphone and those
kids had been hiding their disability
their inability to read and write
by by listening by listening to radio by
having conversations and they were
actually really smart so they were the
best podcast hosts
it was surprising and then we could
celebrate their academic genius because
they were really smart
and then they would start naturally
gravitating toward wanting to learn how
to read and write more but it wasn't
the be all end-all like it is with
standardized tests because without that
you can't take the damn test
so there are ways that i think it
actually works so much better when you
experience now
i'm not talking about theory here i've
been doing this for 17 years and i've
been seeing in the classrooms and all
the kids can
participate in projects and some
projects you can do groups of three
sometimes you need to know that all the
kids do know how to read and write you
know we don't want kids graduating high
school
just knowing how to work a microphone
without being able to read and write so
they're forced to do some credits
in the research they're forced to show
that they have practiced
the academic muscle of research and
writing but if their forte is being on
camera being the one delivering the
content
they're still learning it because to
deliver content you really have to learn
it to memorize it to deliver it to say
it like it's your own right
it's not that easy even if somebody else
wrote it for you so everybody on the
team learns the content
and they actually find that if you speak
to them years after they remember
those media pieces those podcasts those
videos they made
they remember that so much more than
anything else or even a graphic novel
right
pdf graphic novel that stuff that you
take time to draw
that you take time to edit that you
struggle with that you hit your head
against
that frustration and getting through
that frustration building that
frustration tolerance is what our high
schools have to be about
and we have the degree that they want
that we can use to
put some pressure to cause that where it
wouldn't have happened otherwise
yep now thing you didn't really focus on
too heavily but you just mentioned it
here
is these teams and teamwork and you know
as a former business guy
the ability to collaborate with other
human beings is really the number one
human superpower
it's a degree this kind of education
teaches people early on how to really
work together as a team
and create deliverables with you know
something real it's not just
some fake little diorama you create for
a social studies project but something
a significant body of work that alone is
highly valuable in the world of work
that's right and kids really care about
social standing right teenagers in
particular
so if their work is going to be posted
up with other kids from around the world
and it's going to be seen not just by
like that diorama by that one teacher or
maybe that one class
if it's going to be seen by everybody
that actually is an incentive that's
very strong for young people
to motivate them to want to look good
kids want to look good
flat out right and so if they see
somebody else doing something they're
gonna
they're gonna steal and borrow from each
other to look good
in and what we have to do is set up the
incentives
that what looks good is not what is on
social media which is what
inflames you know passions it's really
what
generates academic skills and so that's
this ecosystem that design
actually is being built right now that's
the focus is how do we set up the
incentives
so that young people can be the
investors with their sweat equity
they're investing their time and
attention and that frustration of
getting through the challenges
that investment is the foundation of
this new form of academic capital
and if we can set the data up so that
it's measuring to some extent
how well students overcome those
obstacles and frustration tolerance so
that they have to do that
to gain academic capital and academic
capital that is linked to their degree
then we're starting to drive in the
right direction unlike where
our schools are taking our kids now all
right well now let's make the turn let's
do the reveal
let's start talking about your digital
native
academic ecosystem because from my mind
it's an ecosystem you thought through
most of the components on the sourcing
the evaluation etc so let's
give our audience a five-minute overview
on the essentials of the ecosystem
great so academic capital let me let me
keep going on that thread
in the digital age right it's in the
industrial age we fought wars with you
know by dropping bombs and flying planes
in the digital age
um i'm guessing it's going to be
something like currency wars that we end
up fighting world war iii will be a
currency war about the dollar's value or
something like that
and i'm saying that just because the
digital age brings forth new forms of
capital
so that's just one piece that we have to
notice is that new forms like social
capital right
capital is a form of control ultimately
and so in social capital you become an
influencer you influence other people's
social experience and you measure it you
always have to have some measure with
shares or downloads or followers right
and your audience replaces what the
industrialists would look for in profits
so if you're a startup company and you
have a big audience you get funded now
not so much profits which is what they
used to look for and that's that
dopamine opioid economy that you were
talking about
now that's social capital another new
form of capital is this academic capital
so for high school in particular
students invest that sweat equity
that investment becomes the foundation
of the data set
that measures this form of capital so
instead of likes or follows what we're
talking about is approved credits
to your name that's what you're looking
for in terms of measuring your academic
capital
and we're looking at critical thinking
so can you distinguish signal from noise
can you take something and have a
nuanced position on it
and the key insight that drives this
ecosystem or i call it a platform
is that we're using these 10-minute
chunks of youth media as the building
block of academic capital
and that creates an incentive system
that drives
for high quality student work is what's
being incentivized
in this new sharing loop where you
create and share and get data and you're
practicing that sharing loop that the
entire
digital economy is based on so that's
kind of the 1000 foot overview
of dna credits as an ecosystem yeah and
then we should dive into
taking it from different roles as a
teacher as a student as a
what i call a credit studio somebody
that makes credits what are the
incentives and how do they work
yeah let's do go into the roles because
they're interesting but let's also
talk about sort of a higher level you
know architectural component you
propose that these credits be stored on
a public ledger you know a
uncorruptable public ledger like bitcoin
but hopefully not one that's
accelerating the heat death of the
universe at such a high rate due to all
that mining activity
then students become autonomous owners
of their proof of work
essentially so that let's say they have
accumulated 10 credits in the area of
audio visual production they go look for
a job in that area
or employment as you talk about probably
the world of jobs is
going to continue to go away but gig
employment and audio visual
world they could send the public keys to
those
artifacts of theirs to the hirer and
they could then review the work itself
in a way much more profound than just
looking at a resume
so i think that's important for people
to understand i'm a high school
administrator
right so what the change i'm talking
about here i'm not talking about tearing
down our schools i'm not talking about
anything
radical or crazy we're talking about a
small administrative shift
in sent from moving from a centralized
administration of high school credits to
a decentralized one
the centralized and we haven't talked
about this too much but the centralized
high school credit today has almost no
value
a high school if you don't know the name
of the school if it's a school you've
never heard of it's a public school
somewhere in new york
and you get a transcript and it says
they got this many credits of this you
have no idea what that means and
colleges don't trust it so they need
these ap
exams and sat exams and things to see if
people can actually read
right so the current high school credit
system
is easy to compete with because it's
crap i'm an educator in new york state
so let me just compare
the new dna credits to new york state
credits
so a new york state credit is measured
in terms of hours of classroom
seat time how long you're locked in the
classroom with a teacher that's
certified
right that's not easily adapted for
remote learning it's also not a great
measure
of a credit for dna credits one credit
is earned in one month of full-time work
on a final product so it's 40 hours
times like four and a half weeks so it's
about 180 hours of work
is in one credit the new york state is
108 hours of classroom seat time
now if you assume it's it's kind of
shocking the first thing that i thought
is wait if you're only going to earn one
credit at a time
and you're going to spend one month on
each credit you're not going to get
enough credits in high school well it
turns out if you get rid of september
and june because you need to
welcome and you need to close down the
year from october
to may is 8 months 8 times 4 is 32.
that's 10 credits more than you get in
high school annualized credits
annualized credits in new york state you
get 22 credits to graduate in four years
so this taking six classes at a time
five and a half classes at a time
where the bell rings every you know 40
something minutes you actually get less
credits than if you could just focus on
one project at a time in your last two
years of high school
one month at a time and do quality work
and upload at the end of the month after
multiple revisions
so that's the other piece is this system
requires three revisions minimum
that you upload in the course of that
month so you're doing the that you're
practicing at least three cycles
before you upload the final piece so the
the transcript that you would get is
what you were talking about it's a
transcript or a portfolio that you could
share with employers and
every credit you could click on the
credit if you're online or if you're in
printed form you scan the qr code
and you can see the work that went
behind that credit so you could check
the value of the
the quality of the credit yourself a
university instead of interviewing a kid
or instead of doing anything could
either trust these credits say wow they
got this many of these dna credits
or they can click on each one of them
and see the work itself to see what the
student was capable of doing
so that the transcript itself has the
proof of work built into it
unlike the new york state transcript
that you get right now and say oh what
was your sat score
right because the transcript itself
means nothing not to mention the fact
that in the old system
the teacher that grades you is the same
teacher that's delivering instruction
the same teacher that wrote the content
it's it's
a terrible system because very few
teachers are good at all of those things
in this system the work is graded
anonymously by a committee of three
credit experts
so the teacher is not creating their own
work so students can't guilt trip them
or manipulate them or do anything to get
the credit they have to do quality work
to get the credit
so it establishes this gold standard
high school credit that people trust
because they can verify it for
themselves
and in a world where current high school
credits have
zero value especially now after covid
where we gave away credits last term
when we went online between march and
june because
we just didn't want to hold kids back
because we knew we'd have social
distancing and cutting budgets coming
so we just gave away credits now kids
are expecting to get credits for free
and the high school credits are going to
zero and for people that understand
blockchain it's a very similar
construction
the bitcoin ledger is a ledger of
accounts the person's name how much
money they have right this is the same
thing it's ledger of accounts
your name and the credits so all we've
done is taken the
administration of high school credits
away from the state of new york away
from the states
and put it in the hands of a community
of educators
who are not being re-elected every four
years who can think long-term and think
what's good for our kids
as opposed to the the politicians who
define credits for new york state right
now
who always want the numbers to go up so
they keep watering down the standards
and that's how we just keep
printing too many standards just like we
print too many dollars and we
you know that inflation goes up and now
we have totally inflated grades
that have zero value so it's a really
easy market to compete in
if you you know notice from the book i
believe in capitalism i believe
and greed to drive useful systems and so
the system has to work in a real way to
compete with the high school credits so
all i'm doing is taking the high school
transcript high school credits and
decentralizing the administration of
those credits
i'm not changing anything else by the
high schools or how they're run they'll
adapt
to that change yeah and i was hoping you
were going to be a little bit more
radical
which is to break up these large
granular credits into smaller credits
and i suspect if you don't do that you
may have a
impedance problem when you're a
physicist you know what impedance is
right
how do you actually communicate a whole
credits worth of information in 10
minutes
let me give you an example let's suppose
the person's looking for their
ninth grade civics credit right now
there's a shitload of content
in a ninth grade civics course you know
how a bill becomes a law
you know states counties and local how
do they work together what is federalism
you know
and of course many schools aren't doing
such a good job but i was lucky to go to
one that did do a good job we got a
full year of this kind of civics
education
now in a 10-minute video i might be able
to explain how a bill becomes a law
but i certainly couldn't come even close
to surfacing all the things
you really ought to learn if you're
going to learn the equivalence
of 9th grade civics so is there
impedance mismatch between the content
on one
side of a standard high school credit
and the delivery vehicle
a 10-minute podcast so when students
flip from it's a great question
when students flip from being consumers
of content to creators of content the
change is from focusing on the content
that they need to consume
to focusing on the skills they need to
build like muscles the mental skills
the academic skills for that context so
for civics
what would be the skills that we'd want
students to master
to understand civics and then we want to
set them up in situations if it's an
election year we want them to go to
campaign appearances or actually have
experiences
of civics not talking about civics we
want them involved with civics in a real
experience
and then their the the ten minute
podcast is
their engaging those skills so
it's a matter of redefining the credits
in terms of academic skills that we want
them to master
and then they will you know remember the
content that they interact with much
more than if they had to memorize a
civics you know textbook for a test
but they will also gain some genuine
curiosity and interest in the content
because they'll understand the
importance and they'll have that
experience of
how much power they have or don't have
or what the problems are with the system
by interacting with it in reality not in
a textbook
on the other hand they may learn some
good things but they may not learn the
things that
all the way back to jefferson were
thought to be indispensable for good
citizenship which
first and above all else is how does the
machinery of state
actually work i mean if a person doesn't
know how a bill becomes a law
and you know how the legislative
executive and judicial
our checks and balances on each other
pretty hard to be a citizen
so i would say that yes this
experiential learning is
very good and very valuable but there is
also
just some plain old content which if
we're going to prepare our young people
to be first-class citizens they're going
to have to absorb it's not clear to me a
10-minute video for a whole semester's
worth of civics is likely to accomplish
that
if you have an interview set up with
somebody involved in civics a politician
for example and my students interviewed
new york city politicians frequently
to sit down to the interview you had to
have done enough research and understand
enough not to sound like a fool
right and so you have to understand
enough about how bill becomes a law you
have to go back and do that research
to prepare your questions to then go
back and edit the final product
if you're going to get the credit right
so the credit can have built into it you
need to demonstrate that you
showed up to the interview with some
understanding now are we going to be
able to
have standards that have our checklist
to say did the student do the students
know
this particular piece of content and
this one no that that's an
old industrial way to do things and i
don't think it's working because
people you ask people what they learned
in high school about this stuff and they
don't remember any of it
so what we're doing is looking at brain
research and how people actually learn
to make sure that they're learning
something meaningful that sticks with
them so that they are an
active participant in civics for the
rest of their life that's the outcome
that we want
is them to be and then if you're
actively participating you over time
learn more and more nuance about how the
system works because you interact with
where it's not working
okay that's i think reasonable like
anything else i'm a great empiricist
and i'd say try it and see if it works
right and you've been trying it
we have been for we have been right so
that's it's when you see the kids work i
think the difference
in me sharing those people and people
that haven't experienced it is i've seen
all the hundreds and hundreds of videos
these kids have produced
music video i mean some of the most
moving stuff for music videos and i
would say
how in the hell can you make a music
video to cover
civil rights and then you see what you
know if you've ever seen
on youtube there are these guys that do
the challenges between
historical figures epic rap battles of
history have you ever seen any of those
i've heard of them but i've never
actually seen any of them those are the
kind of things that students make
and you and you watch one of those
they're they're three or four minutes
they're very short
and you can get that the people that
wrote that content knew the history they
had to study that to put it
together and to write that rap
and so that's the kind of content i've
seen it you have to experience it it's
just like i'm saying about the kids and
learning
you have to experience this kind of
content to see how three or four minutes
can convince you that this kid learned
something
about the content and epic rap battles
history i think are the greatest example
of what i think high school
students should be producing they're
irreverent they're intelligent
they go into depth the production
quality is high i think that's
that's the kind of stuff i imagine
coming out of our high schools i'm at a
much higher rate than it is now
very interesting well let's go down into
the details a little bit further we
talked about the fact that these
credits would be stored on a public
ledger where they couldn't be corrupted
and they could always be
accessed and distributed by the students
to whoever had a need to
have access to them the role of the
teachers you renamed
catalysts as i recall talk about a
little bit how the
classroom teacher changes their role
quite dramatically in this
system yeah so a system like this just
like when you
opened up taxis with uber you suddenly
had a lot more people becoming drivers
so there's what i call catalyst in the
book is a coach
is somebody that's helping the young
person with the podcasting or video
editing with the digital
literacy skills right the old literacy
was reading and writing new literacy
involves editing
and you know discerning videos and so
they're helping with those digital
native skills because some classroom
teachers won't have that
and so this system offers them a coach
that works like
tech support you know online coach that
supports them in those pieces so that a
classroom teacher can take on these
projects even if they don't know how to
produce a podcast or make a video
themselves
the catalyst plays the role of the
educator of the
digital native skill set now a classroom
teacher a younger classroom teacher
might be able to do that themselves and
so they can sign up onto the system and
tell the kids hey when you sign in
list put me as your coach and then
that teacher by becoming the coach gets
to access some of the benefits some of
the incentives of the system
a teacher that doesn't participate as a
coach that just
does lets the students choose a project
from the system and supports them in the
academic
research academic skills whatever they
are research or
writing or delivering content that
common core standards have speaking and
listening so the current standards work
very well for these credits
those teachers would get the curriculum
for free they wouldn't have to write the
curriculum
it would be a project-based curriculum
and they would get out of having to
teach to test
a kid instead of sitting for an ap
history exam could get the option to say
hey
you could either sit for the ap test or
you can make an ap video
that's certified by the the college
board and upload to them and they grade
it
and so the students could choose whether
they make a video for the class or the
whether they take a test for the class
and it would be a number of videos
because if it's a
you know nine month course they would
make you know nine videos over the
course of the
of the nine credits so the classroom
teacher has a few options now if they
choose to be that digital coach
the incentives are very strong because
they then if you become a digital coach
and you become very effective that all
your students
that you coach earn the credit which
means that when you told them that they
thought their work was
ready to be uploaded that anonymous
committee of
credit experts when they evaluate say
hey yes indeed you were right that one
is ready for a credit that earns a
credit
a teacher that reliably does that then
can flip over to the side of being a
credit expert
based on their track record of showing
performance with students
actual students producing these credits
and when you are a credit expert you get
paid
30 bucks per 10 minute piece you
evaluate so depending on how long it
takes you to grade a 10 minute piece
and just say credit no credit you're not
giving a 60 or 70 or any of that
you're just saying one or zero credit no
credit pass or fail
um and and you can make a nice side
hustle in the evenings instead of
becoming an administrator
like i did becoming a principal you can
stay in your classroom and a few nights
a week or a few days on the weekends you
can grade pieces
and make up to 180 bucks an hour doing
that and that's what decentralized
administration of credits looks like
instead of these people working for the
department of education with all their
union
stuff that ends up focusing on adult
interests not on what's good for the
kids and on political interests
these people work from their homes kind
of like uber drivers or airbnb hosts
grading work that they are experts in
grading and then getting paid for that
so there's an incentive to become one of
those catalysts
but also as a classroom teacher you can
use the system
just to get high quality curricula and
have to do a lot less work yourself
including grading the final project you
don't have to even do yourself so there
are incentives
yeah both ways and one thing i liked a
lot about your system
being a person who understands human
nature a little bit i think
you need checks and balances right when
people are as you say the teachers are
doing the teaching and they're doing the
testing and they're doing the evaluation
hmm right right your system had
what you called gatekeepers were there i
think you had another name for them too
i don't remember
what it was for the people who approved
or didn't approve the artifacts
talk a little bit about that and
particularly how do you get a
standard of quality that a community of
gatekeepers
are more or less in agreement on because
it would be very unfair
if this gatekeeper would pass this
artifact and this gatekeeper wouldn't
that would be a
sort of a fundamental flaw in the system
right yeah and
gatekeepers sorry what i called when i
wrote the book gatekeepers were now
calling working with the the app is
actually being built in the app they're
called
credit experts so i was talking a little
bit about that before so each piece is
graded by a committee of three of them
it's anonymous they don't know each
other so they can't talk to each other
about and the students don't know who
they'll be
they grade and at the end of the month
when the final grades are in
and they've been put in then the credit
experts get to see
if there are three of them if they voted
with the majority or not right
so if they voted a credit and said it
was worth the credit but the other two
credit experts said it wasn't worth the
credit
it's in their interest to go and study
where the discrepancies were because if
they do that too many times they will
lose the right to continue evaluating
credits because
they're they're saying something's worth
the credit when it but two other people
are saying it's not
um so they then and then they can learn
who each other are and talk to each
other after the credits are finally in
and that's kind of how they grow and
normalize their practice
now remember they're being paid for this
so there's an incentive to keep the
credit
um and let me step back a second they're
being paid and there's a credit studio
who wrote the curriculum who wrote the
credit and who set the standard saying
this is what
a piece needs in order to be accepted
here's how you look for the
students practicing the skills in order
to accept this as a credit
now that credit studios reputation is
based on the quality
of student work because you can go into
that credit you can see all the people
that have uploaded work and gotten a
credit for it
and so as a high school principal i
would go into a system and watch a few
of the pieces before i decide if my
students are gonna be allowed to use
this credit in my school
so the credits themselves need to
maintain a high standard if their credit
experts if their gatekeepers start
giving away credits for free
the quality of that credit is going to
diminish and it will lose value and so
it's that crowd source that crowd
intelligence thing
that the crowd is going to determine the
quality because everyone can see the
credits
and so everyone can watch and say wait
this is like
you know look at these how how is this a
credit they didn't know what the student
didn't do anything
so instead of the current system which
is
top down and kind of um you know
they're surveilling the teachers and
trying to monitor and
and you know it's very oppressive the
way teachers are asked to produce data
right now
this is a surveillance approach where
the people the teachers the students the
parents the universities everybody's
looking at this stuff
and they can see when something has no
value or when it does have value so that
verification happens in a decentralized
way
with these credits rather than a
centralized way if that makes sense
yeah they don't want to be too cynical
but why wouldn't the reaction in some
cases be for the principal to look for
the
lowest level of passes right you know
everyone wants to have no child left
behind so
say there's a you know 100 civics
templates competing with each other
what keeps the principal from selecting
the easiest past one rather than the
most
rigorous well because parents then would
see the type of work that's being
produced to that school
now in the school system that that city
might say hey you need to only you can
only prove the ones that we've reviewed
and we've approved
or you could have someone like the
college board saying these are the ones
we approve and the parents are gonna say
hey i want my kids to have college board
certified ap
credits i don't want them getting you
know some other credit made by
some librarian somewhere that you know
so there's it's again that the pressures
of the system is based on the ecosystem
incentives are designed to drive quality
of the student content
and so if you don't have quality student
content your credits will just not be
noticed or not be in demand
and if you're a principal that chooses
to have lower quality
credits that's going to be obvious by
the type of work that you're you know
when people go to study your institution
they're going to see the type of
institution you are quite openly
and not to mention the city or the
district is going to look and say
what is this why are you choosing why
are you choosing these credits
right because it's they're going to be
held to the fire by the parents
and the students frankly who want higher
quality credits
yeah i can see the curation would
certainly help you to say this one's
been approved by
harvard right exactly if you want to
have your credit counted at harvard it
has to be here
what we would probably see in such an
ecosystem that's why i called it an
ecosystem it's more than just a platform
that's right because
if it's an ecosystem there can be life
evolving outside of the
formal protocols of the initial system
itself so it actually gets richer over
time
in a way that uber only slightly does
you know a true ecosystem gets much
richer over time than uber has
right in terms of the number of things
it's built one of the things you might
expect
is for there to be you know independent
bodies that then certify these templates
as you say that's called the ivy league
consortium or something it says
exactly you know this set of themes is
acceptable to the ivy league and then
you're going to see
all the sub ivy's adopted and all the
tier one restate your research
universities adopt that same
curation standard and then for high
schools
where any percentage of the people are
looking to get accepted to at least the
tier one state school
pretty much gonna have to go with that
curation standard something like that
right otherwise i could see
frankly not all principles are great
everything is on a curve
and unless there are some checks and
balances it would be easy to see
principals take an easy way out
and going for the easy templates with
the soft gatekeeper
no doubt and think of it from the
college border from harvard or from
apple even right if you want
having that having that name on the
credit will give it some prestige
so they have some influence in the
system to say hey here's our brand of
critical thinking
but instead of having to create the
content they can just go and look for
which teachers have produced something
that they really love
based on the student work that's
produced so some teacher working out in
kansas
might produce a really great curriculum
that the college board then grabs and
says hey we're approving we're putting
our staff of approval on this one and
that teacher
is getting recognition and making money
for their work that they had just been
doing with their own students and now
students across the country can benefit
from it because the college board has
said this is now an ap credit
so the college board gets this source of
creativity of decentralized innovation
that they can just look and curate the
best stuff because everybody wants to
have their label on it
rather than them having to from the top
down create these standardized tests
that evaluate whether people are smart
or not right
the college board if they look at this
there's a huge incentive to trade
grading right now you pay them to grade
an exam instead have that pay them to
grade a video
and that video content they can just
look and grab the best stuff because
what teacher wouldn't want the college
board to put their stamp of approval on
it there's nothing to lose
yeah i think building out these other
aspects of the ecosystem will be
necessary
to cause the system to converge to
quality which you make it very clear
that you want the other question i had
as i was reading is
hmm the idea that the gatekeepers or the
credit experts are anonymous
if we want them to have skin in the game
why not put their name on what they
approve
right because so now they're anonymous
during the grading once the grading is
closed at the end of the term you can
see who it is
right ah okay as long as they're
accountable for what they approve
and so you know they started proving
and everybody knows they approve
and then people say hey we're not
going to hire you to be our
credit expert anymore because you proved
right well the system can actually
just say anytime there's one of the
three you know there's two other people
grading this piece if you come out lower
saying it was worth the credit and the
other two come out
not the credit studio is going to revoke
your
credit expert you know approval to get
in there and approve credits and have
them in your queue
so you you know that two other people
are gonna be holding you accountable and
you'll get to see who they are when the
credits are done and you can't change
them anymore you don't want them talking
to each other and you know
fixing it but once the grades are in and
kind of you know in on the blockchain
and hard and fast and can't be changed
then
they need to learn and that's when they
can go and talk to each other and find
each other and see what they were
thinking
yeah yeah okay good so i've
misunderstood it so as long as the
credit expert is not anonymous on the
blockchain then i think the ecosystem
tendency to converge to quality will
work and there's less pernicious
potential collusion i'd say that you
know that right you know there's a fair
amount of game theory where even if you
don't know who the other people
are you realize you all have kind of a
prisoner's dilemma situation we'll all
be sleazy right
and if we're all sleazy we all get paid
off so there are some ways to collude
even in ways that are anonymous so uh
having that second
thing that the uh the certifiers have to
be
public in their certifications after the
fact i think is important
yeah and all of these things i i was
very skeptical of
a lot of this distributed governance
stuff and bitcoin is really what
had me start writing the book and figure
this out i can't i just don't can't
believe that bitcoin exists
right that the incentives worked out so
that we can decentralize
money if you can do it to money you can
do it the high school credits
um maybe
the issue is that money is actually easy
because it's a fungible product you know
every dollar is like every other dollar
uh you know every credit's not like
every other credit every student's not
like every other student
so i would say it's actually going to be
a lot harder to build the governance
mechanisms
and the guard rails on your system than
it was for bitcoin
bitcoin is actually remarkably simple
it's one of those things when i read
satoshi's paper a couple of months after
it was published i slapped myself in the
forehead and said
damn why didn't i think of that right
but your system is going to have
because of the fact that all the
elements are unfungible it's going to be
a lot harder it's a this is a squishier
problem but bitcoin is at least
existence proof
that things of this sort can work so
that that right makes us hopeful
now the other obvious question to sort
of think about the structure
is how does it deal with potential for
cheating right what keeps a fluent
parent from hiring a
hollywood video producer and you know a
you know top-notch new york city script
writer to work with their kid to produce
a knockout video
right well i mean it's the same thing
that happens now with you know tutoring
for it you know to
you can get tutored now to ace these
tests without really knowing much of
anything you just learn how the tests
work
in this system it's the what we haven't
talked about is the anti-bias piece of
um how these blocks are formed
and we want this to be a world where
what zip code you come from should not
determine
your educational outcomes right that's
the ideal
and so what the system does is says
let's start operationalizing that and
measuring how effectively we're doing
that
um by saying how many kids in each zip
code are earning these credits
and let's require for example this is
the um the
the anti-bias criteria will be set by
students but it could be for example
that every
zip code has to have a comparable number
of them to form a block
they can get the credits okay you can
earn the credits without being part of a
block
and we haven't talked about the basic
income piece but if the students get to
be part of a block
on the academic capital blockchain they
form a block of academic capital
that means they're going to be paid out
in this internet funny money for 25
years they're gonna
get basically a basic income of money
that's not worth anything unless they
make it worth something so
cryptocurrency
which will have whatever value the
community creates it to have
so every zip code would have to
participate equally so if the bronx in
new york city
only gets one of these certain types of
credits then only one person from each
other zip code could get one of those
credits
and so people that want a game system
have to then
be incentivized to help people in every
zip code game the system
you can't just help your zip code if you
want to get this basic income and form
academic capital which is kind of the
most prestigious part
of these credits there are a lot of
credits though that will be the system
that will never form blocks of academic
capital they'll just be credits
on your portfolio and so for those
individual credits
sure uh private school could have a
editing lab and could have hollywood
producers
just like when we did the robotics team
some of the teams had
you know their teams met at general
motors fabrication plan with laser
cutters and
they had advantages that we didn't have
that's going to be a reality in
producing high quality content
but it's much easier to fake it on a
test than it is faking on a video where
you're
on you know when you're producing the
video and you know it's
that you can't just copy and paste
somebody else's video where you can't
just learn how to game the system the
student would have to learn enough about
video production
yeah they can hire tutors and coaches
certainly and to get an advantage
that is that that is going to be part of
most systems
of uh high stakes data yeah although of
course in artifacts it may actually be
easier to cheat
you know at least in a test you have to
stuff it into your head if only for one
day
with an artifact and frankly you could
other than the
being the having a person on the screen
all the rest could be
cheated you know they would have to be
pretty pernicious cheating the
adults involved would have to know their
chain because there's three revisions
that they're doing so they'd have to
kind of do a
low quality version first to upload and
get some feedback they'd have to go
through the process with this coach
somebody would have to really be
interested in um and have this cheating
mentality of pretending of faking to be
the student
throughout the month of three cycles of
revision and throughout the
communications and you have to
you know pretend to be them in the
discussions and in the feedback sessions
and right
so it's to produce to have a team
produce content
there's a lot of interaction that
happens and so to get somebody to sit in
for you and all that interaction is
really a
you know a pretty deep level of cheating
that somebody that an adult or a movie
producer would have to be involved with
but of course as we've seen uh the
length some parents will go to
you know that's the thing that's
ridiculous so something something
happened i did have two ideas on how to
push back against cheating one would be
to develop
partnerships with the tool companies and
or build a meta
app and meta app would be much better
because that we could plug any software
tool into it
that literally monitors the student
doing the work you know uses the camera
does some machine learning on the
keyboard sequences etc
and builds a verification file attached
to the
work product which if there's any
question by the
content experts the credit experts they
could then dig into this
audit file and see was that the kid
himself
doing the typing or doing the audio
editing
etc and then another one which may
actually be
better because it's so simple and yet so
powerful is have associated with each
one an
oral examination kind of like you know
the phd oral exam but
five minutes worth oxford yeah and it'd
be really hard to fake
an oral exam right say well how did you
use audacity to do this editing and they
go huh
what's audacity well guess what the kid
cheated right so anyway i'm just
thinking about ways
because again i'm a person who's always
thinks in terms of evolutionary theory
and evolutionary theory always points us
to arms races
and to cheating and so those are some of
the ideas that i had at least and i'm
sure there are plenty of better ones
i love those ideas one of them actually
we've talked about so the team that's
developing this app one of the things
we've talked about is you know gym
credits or
mental health or physical health credits
can you plug in external apps
exercise apps foot counting apps
mindfulness apps and if it's a
mindfulness what stops the person from
saying they're meditating and they're
not
to get their health credit right um and
so we were talking about you know so you
could point the camera yourself and and
have some ai and face recognition right
so these things are coming about now the
beauty of the system of a decentralized
system
i can never pretend to be smart enough
to imagine the types of credits that
come
on board so if cheating becomes a
problem the value will go to credits
that
have anti-cheating protocols like you
were talking about the credit could
actually be a live
podcast where you're interviewed right
by the coach that coach you through the
process
and the interview that live interview is
actually the audio that's uploaded
so i think people like you who are much
smarter than me will come up with ways
to design
credits that solve these things and the
decentralized system instead of counting
on one
pretty thick headed department of
education and what they can imagine and
what they can allow and what they can
you know
you know see as rounds of possibility
you're decentralizing hey anybody that
can come up with
a credit that is more verifiable um and
that prevents cheating and levels of
playing field
will get a market advantage and that
credit will get more people submitting
to it more people demanding it and then
more money running through it
um so yeah i think that i think there
are going to be a lot of innovations
like that that i can't imagine but a
system like this that's just the rails
just the infrastructure
that's exactly what i tend to allow is
that kind of intelligence there's
clearly people smarter than me that are
going to come up with answers that i
can't imagine that and the system is
designed to welcome them
ah that's a very good answer because i'm
a believer that if you set the ecosystem
up such that the incentives within the
ecosystem produce
aim for good value then sooner or later
the problem will be solved so as you
describe that that makes sense
so those people who publish templates
for credits
some of them may have some of these
anti-cheating mechanisms built in
right exactly they could have the either
application monitors or they could have
oral exams or they could have
who knows what ekgs you know that's
right who knows what the future may
bring but yeah if you have the ecosystem
such that
there are incentives for the template
producers to
you know make them as secure as possible
and they can compete on their
security as well as the other aspects of
the process
then over time you would hope that the
ratchet of competition would move the
system towards a better and better place
and you are absolutely right
there is nobody smart enough to figure
all this stuff out in advance it's all
one step at a time one step two steps
forward
one step back complex systems are
inherently unpredictable
and you know the only reasonable way to
proceed is via
empiricism and experiment right and
having an increasing the number of
experiments being conducted and that's
what this intends to do is just
explode the number of credits that we're
trying to see which ones work
and remember what we're competing
against in this covet era people are not
going to go sit in a room to take an
exam together
they're not getting crammed into a room
with no windows to take exams much more
so people are taking these exams on
computers at home
possibly so how do you insure the
security how did like it's
it's so easy to cheat on the ap exams
now you can get your uncle to sit down
and take the exam there's no way for the
system not to know that so
that issue of cheating um in as we go to
more decentralized learning
what we want to do is create the right
incentives so that the problems are
solved within the ecosystem like you
just described
but it's all based on the incentives
rather than on any top-down system we
just want to create a decentralized
community that is interested in this and
tries to solve it because their own
interest
would be served yeah that i think is
exactly the right way to think about it
you talk about that the credit experts
would either pass or fail zero or
one why not a trinary a pass high pass
and fail
so it's interesting you say that so
there is kind of what you're talking
about in there so there's just pass or
fail there's just one or zero
but there is that incentive to get on to
to create a block of academic capital
and when you create a block of academic
capital again you get 25 years of this
basic income put into your wallet in
cryptocurrency
so there is a actual incentive for young
people to want to get onto these blocks
and the only way to get onto the block
aside from the
meeting the anti-bias criteria is to go
above and beyond
on a certain credit so if you're if the
people grading your credit say this work
didn't just earn the credit they went
above and beyond you actually get a fast
track to get into that basic income
opportunity
so there's really just pass fail and
above and beyond and that above and
beyond is is intended to
encourage kids to go further not because
right now you know in so many schools
you just want to do the bare minimum
to get past um and so we wanted to put
an incentive in to have kids go way
beyond
in a month if in that month they can you
know go deeper than they were expected
to
and show off that there is actual
financial prize waiting for them for the
ones that do that
you know i have to admit i read it twice
your theory about this
funny money blockchain ubi i think you
called it a b.i.g
and i was not convinced i'll give you a
chance to make your case
explain what it is first and why you
think it would work so
it's important that our educational
system first let me just say that we
talked about a little bit but
having diversity of thought in a
classroom
if you have if you're in a big city if
you're out in the country it's a
different thing but if in your community
there is diversity but in your classroom
there is no diversity
there is a huge piece of education
that's being missing if everybody thinks
the same way in a classroom it's much
better if you have
diversity of thought to generate you
know the kids that come out of that
diverse classrooms
will have um you know many social skills
and understand different cultures in
ways
that are very important so i think that
diversity is kind of a foundation to
critical thinking and i was looking at
how to incentivize
critical thinking in that sense how to
incentivize students to go and find
people different from them and have
conversations with people that don't
think like them
to generate this content rather than
just staying within
comfortable familiar ways of thinking so
the basic income
is generated to students that form these
blocks of academic capital a block of
academic capital is just a bundle of
student work
every three months that has met certain
criteria
that work that meets the criteria within
a certain geographic region
get bundled form a block and everybody
in that block then for
25 years gets these disbursements and so
the incentive
was to go beyond just earning a credit
and start generating
academic capital um that was a deeper
kind of more prestigious like an award
every three months there's an award and
you can see who wins the award
i'm not attached to this entire system
being on a blockchain anything like that
it could end up on centralized databases
i don't give a damn
i want the time with the platform to
work i don't care about the
i'm not thinking technology first but
for students
to run a blockchain a these bundling of
credits every three months
that they design the criteria of what
puts together a bundle
i think gives them an experience of
decentralized currency and a
participation one that i think is an
important part of their
learning in high school to learn that
they can take their sweat equity invest
it
and get a return on their investment in
some real way with such an intangible
thing as effort or frustration tolerance
overcome
and actually get this these coins
distributed them every month after that
i thought was an opportunity to offer an
incentive to young people
to interact with kind of new generation
currency
and to think about diversity and
critical thinking in a deeper way so
that they're owning the process rather
than having the
educational system own that so that's
where i was coming from is just to
create
an incentive structure using a
blockchain basic income now i also think
that the foundation of the digital
economy
is going to be in education the
communities that have a good education
system
right that students really maintain
their love of learning learn that
work ethic and frustration tolerance are
the ones and that can generate high
quality content
are the ones that are going to do well
in the digital age so it's important
for us economically to have good
education
and so the question was how do we
incentivize
um yeah so that's that that's where i
was coming from is in terms of setting
up the incentives
um using the blockchain using that basic
income
award i kind of went around in circles
and confused myself i think
was there something specific that didn't
make sense to you about it or something
that
um yeah yeah let me give you two
specific critiques and then
uh maybe a more general one first
because of the way
you know way money supply works versus
gdp etc as you point out there's only a
relatively small amount
of growth in currency per year you said
two percent
my own work says five to six percent of
the money supply could grow each year
still a relatively small amount relative
to any given economy even a
pseudo economy or simulated economy so
it's going to be a quite elitist
small number of people that get these
grants
in the current world and is that what we
really want is to be encouraging
hyper competition for a small percentage
of the kids
rather than a more egalitarian way of
cooperating to
do the best we all can together that's
number one number two
and this is probably the deeper critique
is funny money that is not yet
convertible to any other currency not
useful for any transaction
actually going to be an incentive for
you know fairly hard-minded high school
kids
looking together to put five bucks
together to buy a six-pack on friday
right those are two great points so the
first point we're talking about only
high school so these are
out of if we can have a digital cash
system where the
inflation is printed by by putting money
into these kids wallets
high school graduates who are the most
digital native that have produced the
best content
um based on these criteria if we put
into their pockets
it's actually that two percent inflation
or five percent inflation is even better
it's actually not that elite
especially at the beginning of the
system where cash needs to get into
distribution for the you know money
can't be useful unless it's widespread
enough that people
if only one person has all the money
it's really not useful you want to get
it out to a lot of people's hands so at
the beginning
of the system there will be a you know
maybe a 10-year period where you have to
ramp up
to the monetary base and so at the
beginning of the system where it's
unfamiliar
it would actually be almost you know
almost everybody gets a credit could
probably get onto the blockchain
and get this incentive and then as time
goes you would get down to that two to
five percent inflation
rate right now even that two to five
percent inflation rate once you're at a
monetary base
if you're thinking of just high school
kids what percentage of population are
kids graduating high school right now
right that's already
not 100 of the population right and so
two percent
of the monetary base going to or five
percent is even even more exciting
every year being printed it's actually
not that elite if you're looking at
you're just talking about kids
graduating high school that year
getting these incentives so it's
actually a lot more high school kids
than
you might think of you know just two
percent of a globe of a population
globally
i ran the numbers and it was four
percent uh using your two percent number
about four percent would be able to get
a 25
year ubi right so that's once it
stabilizes for the first 10 years
there's incentive for people to get
involved earlier which i think is
interesting because it gets the system
up and running
and then it would be a little bit more
exclusive to get on to it not anybody
again anybody can get the credits and
the credits have their own value as gold
standard credits but to get this ubi to
get this basic income
you would have to be in that more elite
group an elite based on how
diverse how much you can work with kids
around the city
not all kids want to do that work right
to get this if if the criteria is that a
student every zip code has to pass one
of these credits
to do that work you have to coordinate
acro you have to be somebody that's
interested in coordinating across the
city and looking at data across the city
of what people are doing
to ensure that you get the credit and so
not all students are interested in
thinking at that
social level and i that's the thing i
want to encourage i don't think we would
have
a huge number of kids participating but
i think the kids that made an effort too
for example if one of the credits a
thousand kids in every zip code get the
credit then a thousand kids in every zip
code
get onto the blockchain and get this
basic income now they get a smaller
disbursement because they're sharing
that two percent inflation you know
whatever the the system has to print and
money that for that
period but they would all be able to
have part of it so
if it's very successful and everybody
gets it right then they all get a much
smaller
ubi disbursement for each credit and
they would have to earn a lot more
credits to get a meaningful amount of
the cryptocurrency
so it doesn't have to be exclusive in
number of kids it could if a lot of kids
across the city you know get it it's and
it's in that term
in that sense anti-bias that all zip
codes are successfully producing it
then a lot of kids would get this award
and the or just would be worth a little
you know or a lot less
now the point about the currency itself
having no value
i really think i mean i am a believer in
bitcoin and i think if you make a
bitcoin sidechain where from the
beginning
the coin is programmatically set to the
number of satoshi's that it's worth
and over time that um the value goes
down that
encourages people to get off their hands
it should be a cash not a savings
instrument
so the number of satoshi that's worth
over time diminishes because we're
printing more it's an inflationary
instrument
um it encourages people that are holding
these coins to get rid of them so if
over time
more and more of these high school kids
every month are accumulating these coins
and their credit
they're going to have a bigger and
bigger base of people to go advocate to
the
coin exchange say hey accept these dna
coins we're all holding them and the
more people get them the more that
public and the more the customers of
these exchanges will be incentivized to
take these coins and then the coins will
have some real monetary value
but it will be up to the community of
people receiving these coins
so that the risk for the early investors
of sweat equity
they get the biggest disbursement at the
beginning right because the system has
to print a lot of cash in the beginning
and so a lot more people are getting
them and each one is worth a lot more
because the inflation hasn't started so
the incentives at the beginning
it's high risk but high return if these
things do turn into cash you can
actually get a shitload of money from
your high school diploma
if they're successful if they're not and
you never get them turned into cash
you were part of an interesting
experiment taught you something about
economics
but the more people over time that have
these in their wallets the more you know
there's going to be a bigger and bigger
community of people advocating for them
to have some real value and i don't
think that's a huge barrier if we
already define
programmatically how many satoshis
they're worth the exchanges don't have
to do too much work to list them
and then we can start exchanging them
and and because they're you know losing
value over time as cash people would
have an incentive to transact in them
not to hold on to them
i would say maybe interesting you know
my advice from a
uh call it political rhetorical
perspective
would be to sell the dna system
and leave the ubi system for another day
that's great because yeah absolutely in
terms of being in reality the app that
we're building that we have coming out
that i'm playing with this week
it creates these gold standard credits
first with a
ideal of creating this academic capital
these blocks of academic capital
um as an added incentive mechanism for
uh the as it anti-buy so yes you the the
main
gold standard credits are stand on their
own and we'll have to
exist first before we can talk about the
next piece but i do think it's important
for us if we're designing an educational
system to talk about
measuring whether the system is biased
or not and not creating another system
that just
you know gives advantage to rich people
and then doesn't
give any opportunity to leave an uneven
playing field i think it's important for
us to think about that and to have that
in but you're right there are two
separate systems
and they will launch separately with the
credits being first
after being a bit of a fuddy-duddy there
on the uvi let me go on the other side
and suggest that your your platform may
have
a lot more potential for bigger
ambitions than you laid out
as you described it it's a one-to-one
correspondence with
the current high school curriculum but
it seems to me the obvious next move
is to change the granularity to be
arbitrary
right instead of having to be equal to
you know 120
hours worth of civics be able to break
it down into how does a bill become a
law
and you know what is federalism etc and
it's a bunch of micro
credits and each school could choose
what its curriculum looks like
in terms of macro credits and micro
credits and it may well be that the 120
hour or 140 hour
hell it was granularity is is not really
useful in the modern world
and that a different and fractal style
of granularity at different scales
may be the right way to go and then once
you have done that
aha this is the big play it ain't just
for high school anymore this could be
used for the whole world of lifelong
learning
right that's micro credentialing and
there are a lot of organizations that
are trying to do that type of micro
credentialing they don't address high
school
so i think if this idea is successful i
do agree that people will take it and
use it in other contexts i think that's
great
my expertise and my interest is
specifically to end standardized testing
in high schools that's what
my life's work is um and to replace it
with project-based
uh evaluation or and i'm a data person
so data that's based on these projects
rather than on standardized tests
but yeah i think that similar things and
personally i don't think it's going to
come out of
this i think that other people smarter
than me are already developing what
you're talking about for the
professional
work and maybe for uh before high school
i'm not sure and then in terms of the
size of the chunks of a credit i think
it's a good discussion to have and
the system is designed to evolve and
grow over time and get better
the way i launch it at you know at
launch at zero at the
zero state is definitely not going to be
the best way um because
the community will grow and get smarter
without me so i i definitely welcome
thoughts like that to see i i think that
you know just like how
facebook when myspace was out facebook
limited the number of options and made
everything blue and i think that that
worked
better because people wanted to focus on
what they're sharing their community not
figuring out how all these different
pages work and so there's something
about a uniformity for
a high school credit what one credit is
defined as that has of some value in
itself in exchange
for academic institutions but i think
the system will grow and grow in places
that i can't imagine
and it's designed to do that so uh and i
think that ideas like that will happen
that i can't predict now and that we
can't predict now
but you're absolutely right that this is
going to go in directions that that um
i certainly didn't imagine and i think
that's an interesting one is that that
fractal approach i um each one of the
credits could also build that into their
credit
in interesting ways so yeah i think
that's an interesting
place that people like you will think
about and develop things that i'm you
know beyond what i've imagined
well i gotta thank you this has been an
amazingly interesting
conversation you have made a gigantic
probe into thinking different
as old steve jobs would say and i would
actually strongly recommend to the
audience that they go get the book
that what was the name of the book here
education and digital age how we get
there
and the audiobook is coming out shortly
if you prefer audiobooks we should be
out in about a month
yeah my wife uh i'm going to have her
listen to the audiobook she loves
audiobooks i'm uh
amazingly even though i was one of the
people that helped put audible together
i've only listened to one audio book in
my life but anyway
different strokes for different folks
that's right thank you for being on our
show this has been a
really wonderful episode my honor my
privilege thank you jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com